the next eight
videos first appeared in my webinar how
much meat should we eat
the series explores how big sugar and
big meat have fallen in the footsteps of
big tobacco to warp the scientific
process see what the science really says
and how the corporations pay
to manipulate it
[Music]
in 2019 a series of reviews were
published in the annals of internal
medicine that concluded the same thing
that past reviews have concluded
adherence to dietary patterns lower and
redder processed meat intake may result
in decreased risk for premature death
cardiometabolic disease and mortality
meaning the risk of getting and dying of
diseases like heart disease and type 2
diabetes as well as the risk of getting
cancer and dying from cancer therefore
they concluded in their dietary
guideline recommendations
continue your current red meat
consumption continue your processed meat
consumption wait
what
yeah premature death cancer heart
disease diabetes but keep eating your
burgers and bacon
to understand what just happened we have
to go back
to 2015. the dietary guidelines had just
had the audacity to recommend people
reduce their sugar intake
imagine you work for the sugar industry
the evidence is overwhelmingly against
you
what do you do
well what did the tobacco industry do
one method involved the tobacco
industry's funding of and involvement in
seemingly unbiased scientific groups to
manipulate the scientific debate
concerning tobacco and health groups
like the ilsi the international life
sciences institute which has enjoyed a
long and serious collaboration with the
tobacco industry
that same industry group shapes
food policy around the world
the international life sciences
institute technically a non-profit with
an innocuous sounding name has been
quietly infiltrating government health
and nutrition bodies around the world it
was created by a top coca-cola executive
and almost entirely funded by goliaths
of the agribusiness food and
pharmaceutical industries after decades
largely operating under the radar the
institute is coming under increasing
scrutiny by health advocates in the
united states and abroad who say it's
little more than a front group advancing
the interest of the 400 corporate
members among them coke and pepsi
so when the 2015 dietary guidelines
advised eating less sugar the
soda-funded international life sciences
institute sponsored a review concluding
that the guidelines on sugar were simply
not trustworthy
who did they pick for this hatchet job
bradley johnston
and here it is published in the annals
of internal medicine the scientific
basis of guideline recommendations on
sugar intake and concluded there
basically wasn't one
guidelines on dietary sugar do not meet
criteria for trustworthy recommendations
as they are based on low quality
evidence
this comes right out of the tobacco
industries playbook cast doubt on the
science said professor marion nessel
this is a classic shameful example
of how industry funding biases opinion
yes
the paper was paid for by the likes of
coca-cola hershey red bull and the
makers of oreos but the authors swore
they wrote the protocol and conducted
the study independently
turns out that was a lie forcing the
journal to publish a corrected version
after the associated press obtained
email showing the industry front group
requested revisions
it also came out that a co-author
conveniently forgot to mention a 25
grand grant she got directly from
coca-cola
you know it's bad when candy bar
companies criticize an industry-funded
paper on sugar the makers of snickers
skittles and m m's broke ranks with
other food companies and denounced the
industry-funded paper they themselves
were a member of the isli but
come on telling people to ignore
guidelines to cut down on sugar that's
just making us all look bad
if you look at the relationship between
funding source and the conclusions in
nutrition related scientific articles
there's like seven or eight times the
odds that the conclusion will skew
favorably compared to studies with no
industry funding
for interventional studies the
proportion of studies paid for by
industry that reached unfavorable
conclusions about their own products was
a big fat zero percent which should not
surprise anyone
so what can journals do to counteract
the tactics that industry often uses to
advocate for the safety of unsafe
products or question the integrity of
science that calls their products into
question
to combat the tobacco industry's
influence over scientific discourse
leading journal editors have refused to
be passive conduits for articles funded
by the tobacco industry they just won't
accept tobacco industry funded studies
period
accordingly high quality journals could
refrain from publishing studies on the
health effects of added sugars funded by
soda and cookie companies
but they're not
this was published in the annals of
internal medicine
and so
four years later with the next batch of
dietary guidelines on the way and the
last scientific report of the guidelines
committee encouraging people to eat
diets not just lower in sugar but lower
in meat as well
big beef decided to follow in the
footsteps of big butterfinger same
journal
same guy same scientist for hire bradley
johnston as lead author and the rest is
history
we'll dig into exactly how he pulled it
off
next
[Music]
you